using the classical tools of a straight
edge and compass for which n can we
divide a circle into n parts of equal
area
if we start playing around with this
problem at first it doesn't seem too
interesting we can construct two
antipodal points on a circle and that
divides the circle into two pieces of
equal area
we can construct an equilateral triangle
on the circle and that will allow us to
divide the circle into three pieces of
equal area
proceeding in a similar manner we can
construct the regular square
on the boundary of the circle dividing
the circle into four pieces of equal
area
and then we can do the same thing with
the regular pentagon and the regular
hexagon dividing the circle into five
pieces of equal area and six pieces of
equal area respectively
we might think we can continue this
pattern and just construct the regular
heptagon on the circle which then
divides the circle into seven equal
pieces
but there's a problem here it turns out
the regular heptagon is not
constructable using the classical tools
of a straight edge and compass
so that leaves us with a question can we
divide a circle into seven equal parts
using just a straight edge and compass
let's find out
start with a line segment that will
serve as the diameter of a semi-circle
like this
then divide the diameter of the
semicircle into seven congruent pieces
which can be done with a straight edging
compass let's call the length of these
pieces d
after bisecting segments when necessary
use the compass to construct these
nested semicircles for a total of seven
pictured semicircles
let's compute the area of the
semicircles first the first semi-circle
has area pi times d squared over eight
the second one is four pi d squared over
eight then nine pi d squared over 8 and
so on each time we have the nth square
times pi d squared over 8.
if we call the area pi d squared over 8
the value x
then the areas of the circles are x 4x
9x 16x and so on each time we have the
next square times x
we can use these values to determine the
areas in the circle the first region has
an area of x then 3x then 5x 7x and so
on each time we're taking the difference
of successive squares to get the next
odd number
and now we apply our trick
this time we construct the exact same
regions in the bottom semicircle but
this time from right to left
once we adjoin the regions like this we
see that each of the seven created
regions has an area of 14 times x
that means that each of these regions
has exactly the same area
consequently this means that we have
divided the circle into seven pieces of
equal area using a straight edge and
compass
you